<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honourable actions of that most famous and valiant Englishman, Edward Glemham, Esquire Lately obtained against the Spaniards, and the holy Leauge [sic], in foure sundry fightes. With his landing on S. Georges Ile, belonging to our enemie, which he kept with foure score and six men, the space of 48. houres. With his like succes against 6. gallegoes, of which he fired two: and notable victorie in his fight with foure gallyes, bound for Marceellus: to the eternall honour of our countrie, and no lesse worthy commendations of the valiant and braue minded gentleman and his followers, haning [sic] but one ship of burthen 240. tunnes, or thereabout, whereof himselfe is owner. Published for an encouragement to our English aduenturers, (gentlemen, sailars, and souldiars,) that serue against the euemies [sic] of God and our countrey.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120325</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855524</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01787)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 639:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honourable actions of that most famous and valiant Englishman, Edward Glemham, Esquire Lately obtained against the Spaniards, and the holy Leauge [sic], in foure sundry fightes. With his landing on S. Georges Ile, belonging to our enemie, which he kept with foure score and six men, the space of 48. houres. With his like succes against 6. gallegoes, of which he fired two: and notable victorie in his fight with foure gallyes, bound for Marceellus: to the eternall honour of our countrie, and no lesse worthy commendations of the valiant and braue minded gentleman and his followers, haning [sic] but one ship of burthen 240. tunnes, or thereabout, whereof himselfe is owner. Published for an encouragement to our English aduenturers, (gentlemen, sailars, and souldiars,) that serue against the euemies [sic] of God and our countrey.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[bel] I[effes] for VVilliam Barley, and are to be sold at his shop in New-gate Market,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Honourable actions of Edward Glemham.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Glemham, Edward.</term>
               <term>Adventure and adventurers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21019:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21019:1"/>
            <p>THE Honourable Actions of that moſt Famous and valiant Englishman, Edward Glemham, <hi>Eſquire.</hi> Lately obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the Spaniards, and the holy Leauge, in foure ſundry fightes.</p>
            <p>With his landing on S. Georges Ile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to our enemie, which he kept with foure ſcore and ſix men, the ſpace of 48. houres.</p>
            <p>With his like ſucces againſt 6. Gallegoes, of which he fired two: And notable victorie in his fight with foure Gallyes, bound for <hi>Marceellus:</hi> to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall honour of our countrie, and no leſſe worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of the valiant and braue minded Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and his followers, hauing but one ſhip of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then 240. tunnes, or thereabout, whereof himſelfe is owner.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for an encouragement to our Engliſh aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers, <hi>(Gentlemen, Sailars, and Souldiars,) that ſerue againſt the enemies of God and our Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>A. J.</hi> for VVilliam Barley, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Market. 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21019:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21019:2"/>
            <head>Honourable actions of Edward Glemham, <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt paſt, 1590, that moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and venterous Gentleman, <hi>Edward Glemhall</hi> of <hi>Benhall</hi> in Suffolke, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, ſet ſaile from <hi>Tilberry-hope</hi> neere Graueſend, onely accompanyed with one good ſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Edward</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſtance,</hi> of the burthen of 240. Tunnes or vpward, and one Pinnis called the <hi>Fawlcon,</hi> which Ship and Pinnis he alone equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, furniſhed and victualed, in ſuch ſort and with ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as ſildome hath there beene ſo much prouiſion made for the like Voyage, all at his owne proper coſts. This famous Gentleman, being owner and ſole aduenturer: not onely haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarded his goods to the fortune of the Seas, but ſcorning the Idle life which many deſireth, aduentured alſo his bodye in this voyage, ſhowing his worthie vndaunted minde, which holdeth honour in greater regarde, then eaſe at home, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring countreys benefit, and his reputation farre beyond life, (albeit) his worſhip in his Countrey, and liuings were ſuch, as might haue drawne the coward mindes of many, to haue liued amongſt their freends, free from thoſe dangers immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to trauailers, yea, ſuch were the bountifull bleſſings of God, enduing him with thoſe worldly fauoures, as might haue woone him to haue left his determined voyage, hauing ſo aboundantly the loue generally of his neighbours, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and commons, amongſt whom he kept good hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, feaſting his freends, and releeuing the poore plentifully, ſuch was the good minde both of the gentleman and his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb facs="tcp:21019:3"/>
wife, whoſe worſhipfull aunceſtrie, hath beene, and is, moſt famous, both in Court and Countrie, being daughter and ſole heyre of a right worſhipfull Knight, famous in his life, and of great poſſeſſions. But neither the deſire of liuing which he enioyed, the ſorrow of his right worſhipfull Wife, nor the pitteous mone of his ſweet children, might remooue his ſetled determination from his intended voyage, which he vndertooke this laſt yeare, for the Ilands of the <hi>Suryes</hi> and <hi>Canaryes,</hi> whether at his departure hee framed his courſe, giuing the like directions to his Pinnis, who he was enforced to leaue behinde him at <hi>Douer,</hi> to repaire ſome wants, but he neuer ſawe hir ſince, by the negligence of the Maiſter and Captaine which he left in her, to no little greefe of the Gentleman, &amp; no ſmall diſcomfort to all his company.</p>
            <p>All things furniſhed for his voiage, the great commander of the heauens and ſeas, fauouring his enterpriſe, he ſet ſaile from <hi>Douer</hi> roade, hauing the winde large at North Eaſt, which continued ſo eight daies, ſo that it freed him from our coaſt. Thus happily he recouered the Cape, and from thence to the Ilands, there ſpending his time, dooing ſmall good, vntill <hi>Nouember,</hi> abiding many ſharpe ſtormes of winde and weather, which they continued, when many were enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to forſake the Ilandes, and returne home, keeping the Spaniſh coaſt, without dooing any thing anſwerable to his valiant minde, loathing to returne without dooing ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable exploite, aſwell for honour of his Countrey, as his reputation, his men, healthfull and in good liking, for whom was his cheefeſt care, for that he would profit them, whoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing is thereby maintained, their wiues and families, extee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their good, more then his owne loſſe, which was likely to be of no ſmall importe.</p>
            <p>Houering betweene the Ilandes, commaunded by the harſhnes of the windes, to ſeeke his beſt ſafetie, hauing little chaſe or none, and deſirous to releeue his companies with ſuch freſh vittels as the Ilandes affords, he moſt valiantlye accompted, to land on Saint <hi>Georges Iland.</hi> And hauing
<pb facs="tcp:21019:3"/>
counſelled with his company thereof, they were all willing, as men that loue him, both for his valoure and courteſie, to follow him, in what ſeruice ſo euer, all condiſcending to hys will, he cauſeth ſpeedy preparation to be made for the ſame. And hauing a ſmall Caruill, which he had taken before at his ſtarne, for that ſhe drewe little water, was the fitter for the landing his companies: All things prouided, they attend but the tide for their beſt aduantage, and neere vpon a full ſea, he halled vp his long Boate and the Caruell, into which ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red foure ſcore and ſixe men, 60 Shot, the reſt Pikes, blacke Billes, and other warlike abilliments, and in Gods name commit themſelues to their good fortunes.</p>
            <p>The watch of the Iland, perceiuing theyr comming neere the ſhore, with their Ship, more then commonly any ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dooth, had before giuen warnings, that the moſt force of the Iland was there, ready to receaue them: which our men perceaued, yet could not be daunted with the ſight of them, but valiantly put forwards, attempting to land where they were moſt ſharpely encountered by the enemie. But the Gunner taking aduantage, with a Sacare from the Ship, charged with a Chaine, made ſo good a ſhoote, that hee flew and diſmembred tenne or twelue, who ſeeing his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe aunſwerable to his deſire, hee playde ſtill vpon them with his Ordnance from the Shippe, which made them the ſooner to retire, ſo that the whole conflict at the firſt landing, continued not paſt two houres, when the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards heartes began to quaile, and his men to bee of more courage, which the Spaniards perceauing, ſounded a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate, and with all ſpeede, fled into the hie Countreyes, ſo thankes be to God, they ended onely with the loſſe of two men, beſides ſome hurt, yet did they great ſpoile amongſt the Spaniards.</p>
            <p>Being landed, and night at hande, they had no pollicie, to perſue them, wherefore marching into the lande a Mile or ſomething leſſe, they encamped themſelues, diſpearſing ſundrye Sentenels, for watche, farre from the Campe,
<pb facs="tcp:21019:4"/>
diuers wayes, keeping a ſtrong watch in campe. That if the enimie ſhould haue come vpon them in the night, they might haue beene ready to receiue them.</p>
            <p>But the Spaniards, hauing ſo bad a banquetiat their firſt meetings, had no haſt to come againe. Day being come, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Glemham</hi> commaunded certaine eſpials to be ſent out, to ſee if they could deſcrie the enemie, but they returned with little newes, ſauing they ſaw many armed in no araye, and diuers women and children, carrying goods to hide.</p>
            <p>Vpon this newes, that worthy Gentleman, and braue Captaine, Maiſter <hi>Edward Horecourt</hi> his aſſociate in thoſe his Voyages, willed the Generall to deuide the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and he would lead the one of them: and ſo with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes diſplayed, to march in warlike order farther vp, to ſee what they would do: which counſell the Generall accepted, and with eaſie paces marched on, largely diſtanted one from the other, to make them ſeeme farre more in number then they were, with Drums, Trumpets, and two Enſignes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaid, yeeling ſuch terrible cryes as they marched, as might terrifie a great company.</p>
            <p>The Generall gouerned by Captaine <hi>Horecourt,</hi> whoſe experience in land ſeruice is much, hauing had charge of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the Low-countreys, Ireland, and Portingall, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wholy directed by him, the two Companies marched in ſort like two wings, with intent and full reſolution, if there came ten men for one, to encounter them, and valiantly to die together, or gaine honour for euer with the enemie.</p>
            <p>They had not marched halfe a league, when making a ſtand for ſome parley, the eſpyals brought word they ſawe one come, mounted as if he came to ſpeake with them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Generall ſent a Guarde of Muſketeares to meete him, and to ſtay him, if he had any thing to ſaye, for that hee ſhould not take view of their forces. When he came to this Courte of Guarde appointed to meete him: they demanded what he was? Who anſwered, he had to ſay to their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Captaines, and deſired to be brought to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<pb facs="tcp:21019:4"/>
they ſtaide him there, and ſent worde to the Generall what hee was, who came accompanied with foure other Gentlemen, and his whole noiſe of Trumpets, moſt brauely to ſpeake with him.</p>
            <p>After entertainment giuen him in the beſt manner, for that he ſeemed ſome <hi>Cauelere,</hi> hee aduertiſed the Generall that he came from the Gouernour, to know what they were, and what they required.</p>
            <p>The General vſing him kindely, gaue him milde ſpeeches, but willed him to returne his aunſwer thus. That he was a Gentleman of England, &amp; what he pretended, he would not impart to any priuate man: but if the Gouernor would come himſelfe, he promiſed on the honour of an Engliſh Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he ſhould paſſe and repaſſe in ſafetie: if hee gaue not credit to his worde, hoſtage of reputation, Gentlemen of his countrie, no whit inferiour to the beſt Spaniard in the Ile, ſhould be deliuered for him.</p>
            <p>With this anſwer, the Meſſenger haſtneth to the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: Who calling his Counſell, required their opinions, whoſe aduiſes giuen, he came towards the Campe, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with twelue others, well mounted, about ſome halfe mile from the Court of Guarde, they made ſtaye, and ſent vnto the Generall for his hoſtages, who ss he promiſed, ſent a Gentleman, that ſometimes attended the Earle of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wike, Maiſter <hi>Hammon,</hi> one Maiſter <hi>Gore,</hi> and Maiſter <hi>Hunnings,</hi> Guarded with twentie Muſketeares, who deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the Gentlemen, and receaued the Gouernour, conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to a place where the Generall made his ſtay, diſtant from his Campe.</p>
            <p>Being mette, and hauing a while conferred, the General demanded to haue the Iland deliuered him, vnto the Queen of Englands vſe, which if they would, they ſhould haue liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to depart with what they had there in poſſeſſion, if not, to commit it to the haſſard of the ſworde, for what aduantuge he had, he would keepe, or die for it: and what ſpoile he could make they ſhould be aſſured of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21019:5"/>This demaund the Gouernour flatlye denyed, alledging he was a Gentleman, and ſworne to the King his Maiſter, as the Generall for the Queene of England, and that before his allegiance therein ſhould quaile, he would die with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour like a Gentleman. Yet quoth he, as ye are a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and will fauour me heereafter, what there is in the Ile will do you pleaſure, commaund it, condicionally that your companies ſpoyle not the Kings ſubiects, nor theyr goods, which rather then I may endure, I will hazzard all to my good Fortunes.</p>
            <p>The Generall for that he vnderſtood not the Spaniſh, was compelled to vſe an enterpretor, wherefore that hee might ſpeake his owne minde, he demaunded of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour if he ſpake Lattin, which he did excellent well, ſo in lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, which the Generall ſpeakes as perfect as Engliſh, hee confermed what he had before ſpoken and no more.</p>
            <p>The Generall craued ſome reſpect to anſwer him, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing captaine <hi>Horecourt</hi> and the Maiſter which was new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come aſhore, to accompany him, he called the cheefeſt of all his company, aduertiſing what offers were made, and wild them to looke into the matter with aduiſe, before they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, for as he had brought them thether, he would in part be gouerned by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who aduentured as he did, though his charge was more, yet told them, that in his opinion, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome good end be made, then to aduenture farther, for that they were ſtrangers, not knowing theyr forces, neither the vantage or diſuantage of the place, and to what perrils they were ſubiect vnto, being of no more power, he referred to their directions to conſider. I ſpeake not this quoth the Generall of cowardis, for if I haue but twentie of you to ſtand by me, Saint <hi>George</hi> for all: I will end my life before I diſtaine the reputation of an Engliſh Gentleman.</p>
            <p>The company hearing his reſolute minde, which they euer found, ſuch as he ſeemed, with a generall voice, put it to his diſcretion, vowing (what he did) to ratifie, either to peace, or fight it out, to take part with him ſo far as their liues would
<pb facs="tcp:21019:5"/>
go. The Generall gaue them thankes for their loues, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted that he would want whatſoeuer he had or ſhould haue in his poſſeſſion, before they ſhould lacke. Thus greeued, to deliuer that aduantage which he had in his enemies country, he wiſhed but one hundred men more, to haue tryed h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fortune with them, but he thought it ſmall pollicie, to refuſe thoſe offers, to haſſard their liues and all, conſidering his ſmall power, the enemie being in his owne countrey, likely to be releeued euery day with more ſupply, and they to haue nothing, but what by force they obtained, waying all things with equalitie as well his owne dangers as his companies, he returned the Gouernour this anſwer.</p>
            <p>That conſidering he was a Gentleman, which helde his reputation in ſome accompt with his Maiſter the King, and that it might greatly blemiſh his credit, if they ſhould bid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> battell and ouerthrow them, of which by Gods helpe he was aſſured, he had with earneſt requeſt perſwaded the company to giue ouer their aduantage, on thoſe conditions preſently to be performed, <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhould haue of victuals of al ſorts the Iland affordeth, ſufficient for the vitteling the ſhip, and 1000 Crownes amongſt them, to be deuided in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the loſſe of their men ſlaine at their landing.</p>
            <p>To thoſe conditions the Gouernour condiſcended, and on his credit to deliuer it in one daies reſpect this matter ended. The Generall enuited the Gouernor to ſuch viands as they had, and ſo ſpent the time a while with freendſhip, carrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the health of the Engliſh Queene, and making good cheere, when night approaching, the Gouernour tooke leaue to depart, earneſtly entreating the Generall, and Captaine <hi>Horecourt,</hi> to accompanie him to his houſe, where to ſuch entertainment as the Iland affordes, they ſhould be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and ſo aſſured from any euill to be offered to him, or his company, as if he were in his beſt freends houſe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. But the Generall knowing what it is to truſt a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiled foe, gaue him as hartie thanks as his offers were kinde, yet would truſt him but as a Spaniard, ſo he departed, and
<pb facs="tcp:21019:6"/>
the Gentlemen returned which was deliuered for him, vnto whom the Spaniards had giuen many gifts.</p>
            <p>The Gouernor being departed, order was taken for the watche, which was ſet in diuers places, for feare of treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the night. About two houres in the night, a Trumpet ſounded a parley neere the Campe, which ſo amazed them, that they were greatly in doubt of the Spaniards tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, and betooke them all to armes preſently. The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, according to law of armes, ſummoned him againe with one other Trumpet, then after with his whole noiſe, and ſent Captaine <hi>Horecourt</hi> with a guarde of Muſketteares, to heare the cauſe of his comming, who found none but three men ſent from the Gouernour, with ſuch vyands dreſſed as was puruayed for his owne ſupper, and one But of Canary Wine, which the Generall thankefully accepted, and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the trumpet largely with Crownes, ſent him away.</p>
            <p>The next daye about two of the clocke after noone, the Gouernour came againe to the Generall, accompanied with a troope of Gentlemen, where they paſſed the time in ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting, attending the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the cariages which brought the victuals, <hi>viz.</hi> Beefe, Kids, 30 Buts of Sack &amp; Canary wines, Ruſke, Meale, Flower, Salt, pumpions, &amp; other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, ſufficient for nine moneths victuals. The Spaniard hauing kept his word, the Generall was loath his curteſies ſhould go altogether vnrequited, wherefore he enuited the Gouernour &amp; his company to dinner aborde his ſhip the next day, which the reſt were loth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent vnto, which the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perceauing, told them flatly &amp; halfe in choller, that they did diſtruſt him, but (quoth he) you ſhal not need, for the worſt Engliſhman doth hold his word of honor in as much regard as their king, &amp; that if his boy for him had promiſed any thing he would maintaine it as his life. But Gentlemen (quoth he) ſeeing you ſuſpect my word, &amp; that ye may accept my offer without diſtruſt, for that I would willingly haue your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, my warrant ſhall be thoſe pledges which I will not leaue for the kingdome of Spaine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21019:6"/>The gouernor being of milde nature, was ſorry to ſee him ſo diſquiet: wherefore with gentle words, he firſt pacified the Generall, then entreated his freends to accompany him, which they eaſily graunted, and accordingly came the next day, where the Generall feaſted them in braue maner, to the honour of his countrey, &amp; his owne worthy commendations.</p>
            <p>The day folowing, he that ordained wind &amp; tide to ſerue the purpoſes of men, ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a faire &amp; pleaſing gale, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him the rather to ſet ſaile fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, &amp; ſo ranged alongſt the Ilands againe, ſeeking his good fortune. The 5 day after he put from <hi>S. Georges,</hi> he diſcried two tall ſhips, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue chaſe, with a ſcant gale, all night, vntill the next day at noone, when bearing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the generall hailed them, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtrike for the Queene of England. Thoſe vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains in deſpite ſhewed the Leagers flags &amp; refuſed to ſtrike, whervpon the Gunner ſhot one of them being Admirall, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, betweene wind &amp; water, ſo that ſhe was faine to lie by the Lee, to ſtop hir leake. Then bare the Vizeadmirall vp to reſcue her conſart, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Generall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to ſtrike, but they anſwered diſpitefully they would not, but ere they did yeeld, or ſtrike, they would ſinke in the ſeas: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> company de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded whence they were, they ſaid of <hi>S. Mallowes,</hi> &amp; their names the <hi>Dolphins,</hi> the one the great <hi>Dolphin,</hi> the other the little <hi>Dolphin,</hi> ſtout ſhips &amp; well appointed, the leaſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing 22 caſt peeces: wel quoth the General, ſtrike your flag, for neuer ſhal ſo baſe vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ains as you cary your flag, wher an Engliſh gentleman is: they ſaid they would not, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bare the General with them, &amp; gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their whole brode ſide, &amp; ſhered cloſe with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, entending to haue borded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> negligence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helms ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they fel off, to the Generals great diſcontent. By this time the Admirall had reaſonable well ſtopped hir leake, &amp; ſeeing the General bare with him, made ready to fight, and firſt gaue them their whole ſide, but hit not the ſhip at all, ſo began a hot &amp; mortall fight on their partes, for our men entering, the Admiral ſaw 7 or 8 men ſlaine, and hauled into their forecaſtell, yet by e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p they were put off
<pb facs="tcp:21019:7"/>
againe. But the Gunner whoſe name is <hi>Henrie Greene,</hi> a braue &amp; valiant man, ſo behaued himſelfe, that it was marue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lous to report. And euery man in his place ſo beſtirred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they deſerue commendations. The Maiſter, a man of no ſmall courage, greeued at their putting off, cryed ſtill, aborde, aborde: and at the third encounter the Generall himſelfe with twentie others to reſcue him, borded the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, who being grapled, could not fall off againe ſuddenly. The Vizeadmirall ſeeing her conſort in danger, laide her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borde alſo on the other ſide, entering her men, ſo that our company was enforſed to retyre, with little hurt, &amp; great da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the enemy. Fiue houres continued they this whot conflict; when parting by reaſon of the night comming on, they went away &amp; were neuer ſeene after. This conflict en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Generall calling his company, firſt gaue God thanks for preſeruing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then carouſed he to them, binding them all by their faiths, to fight it out with them the next day, &amp; either to take them, or die for it, to which they willingly conſented.</p>
            <p>Long ſeemed that night, to thoſe which earneſtly looked for better ſucceſſe. The day no ſooner gaue light, but happie was he might firſt looke out to deſcrie them, but in vaine, for their market was marde, and the Frenchmens entertane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo bad ouernight, they durſt not ſtay to take a breake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt the next morning. When the Generall and his company perceaued that they were quite gone, and no hope remained to meete them any more, the winde ſeruing them ſo well, to beare with their owne coaſt, it greeued them not a little, ſo hulling there ſome time, to ſplice ſuch ropes as were periſhed with ſhot, and to amend ſuch hurtes as were done with ſhot likewiſe, which finiſhed, and all things in good ſort ordered, they went for the Northern Cape, to ſee if any better fortune would be fall them: where lying ſometime at Hull, ſomtime bearing ſmall ſaile, houering too and againe, thereabouts, they were chaſed with ſixe Galligoes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who fearſly purſued them, but our Generall being becalmed, and ſeeing no hope to eſcape them, prouided to fight it out.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21019:7"/>The Admirall of this Fleete, ſeeming a braue man, was the firſt that came vp, neuer offering to ſhoote, vntil he laid them aborde, but by the good induſtrie of the Generall, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full working of the Maiſter, M. <hi>Iames Beares</hi> of Graueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, a man no leſſe pollitike then valiant, they were put off againe, and their foremaſt with a demie Couluering ſhotte, borne by the borde. Then the Vizeadmirall and Reare admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, vpon whome their Gunner had plaide and doone much harme vnto, laide them alſo aborde, one of the one ſide, and the other on the other, where they were ſo ſharpely aſſailed, that they loſt many of their men. The Captaine of the Vize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admirall was ſlaine by Captaine <hi>Horecourt</hi> in his owne Galligo, in fight moſt brauelie. The other Galigoes would come vp, and ſhoote often, and away againe, but did little harme, thankes be to God. Three houres and more by eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation endured this fight, when a ſtrong gale at Northeaſt began to blowe, and the ſeas to growe, ſo that perforced to put from them, our Generall cauſed his Gunner to beſtowe diuers Arrowes and pickes of fireworkes among them, ſo that he left them burning, and knoweth not how they did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide it. But diuers Engliſhmen being in ſight of this fight, that durſt not come neere them for feare, to reſcue them, hath reported at their home comming, that Generall <hi>Glem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> his Ship and man were all burnt, whoſe reportes are not of trueth thankes be to God.</p>
            <p>The Generall freed from thoſe bad companions, ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned great harmes, and hauing doone ſmall good for himſelfe and his companyes, was loath to go for England, but deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to go for the ſtraightes, whether they framed theyr courſe, hauing the winde faire to ſerue their turne, yet with very foule and bluſtering weather, in which ſtorme he ſpent his Maine Maſt, which had beene before fyſht: but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of two ſhotte therein receaued, which weakened it the more, he could not ſaue it: and hauing few Harboures with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſtraights to freend, went for <hi>Argere,</hi> where he was moſt roially entertained, in ſuch ſorte, that no Gentleman
<pb facs="tcp:21019:8"/>
of any nation hath receaued the like at any time. There he ſet a Maine Maſt, and puruayed himſelfe of all other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries he wanted, trimming his Ship at pleaſure, wanting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that he could or would deſire. Two moneths verye neere, he remained at <hi>Arger,</hi> or thereabouts, for that hee would haue had the company of the Engliſh Fleete, which could not be ready ſo ſuddenly, wherefore loth to ſtaye any longer, he gaue the attempt to go alone, onely accompaned with a Ship of <hi>Deepe</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> called <hi>The Flower de Luce,</hi> whoſe ayde he promiſed to be. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming neere vnto the mouth of the ſtraightes, without offer to be diſturbed of any. There were foure of the king of <hi>Spaines</hi> gallies bound for <hi>Marceelles,</hi> who eſpying thoſe two Ships, bare with them, as much as might be: and comming within ſhot, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged foure Cannons againſt the Generall, which hit him not. The Generals company being now freſh &amp; luſty, like me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſingular good courage, cheered one the other, affying one God which had bin ſtill their comforts, in whoſe name they gaue a moſt braue and ſharpe onſet vpon them: the Gunner playing ſo well his part, that within leſſe then two houres, he had almoſt ſunke two of them, which compeld them to lie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the carine, to ſtop their leakes, yet all they could do, could not helpe one of them: but they were faine to ſaue their men and ſlaues, and let hir ſinke. All this diſmaide them not, but the other three continued the fight whotly, vntill they ſawe the French ſhip come vp, who ſeeing the Gallies, was loth to put hir ſelfe in daunger, nor neuer offered Shotte, yet prouoked by the earneſt means of certaine Engliſh Sailars they had a borde, they bare with them, which the Galies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuing, doubting how to withſtand both, that had ſo bad ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe with one alone, made to the ſhore with all the haſt they could, which they recouered, &amp; ſo eſcaped. But our generall hauing endured many ſhot, was ſo ſpoiled of his rigings, and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as he was enforced to put lack again to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere,</hi> but the <hi>Flower de Luce,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> ſhip of <hi>Deepe</hi> came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> way, thankes be to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by his meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21019:8"/>Other news there is of his good ſucces, which I may God prooue true, for the Gentlemens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; his company, as there is no doubt made the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; his home comming dayly expected, which God grant may be ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and in ſafetie.</p>
            <p>Thus freendly Reader haue I breefely tourned the fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſucceſſe of this worthy minded Gentleman, in this his firſt voyage to the ſeas, whoſe troubles haue beene ſuch, by Fortunes croſſes, as might cauſe many a man to ceaſe his trauailes, &amp; to liue at home in content, yet this I aſſure you cannot diſmay him at all, ſo braue and reſolute is his vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered minde, rather deſiring honor and his countries good, then life with great poſſeſſions, whoſe worthye minde God encreaſe in all Gentlemen of his calling, ſo ſhall our Prince be moſt honorably ſerued, and hir ſubiects gaine fame, thorow the whole world by their prowis, to Englands eternall honor.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>H.R. in commendation of the right worſhipfull and valiant Generall, <hi>Edward Glemham,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BRaue men at Armes, Englands <hi>Cheueleers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let <hi>Glemhams</hi> honors, mongſt you be of name,</l>
               <l>Whoſe conqueſts gainde, gainſt Spaniſh <hi>Caualiers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With goulden Trumpe eterniſd is by fame:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turkie, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> reports the ſame.</l>
               <l>To Englands honor <hi>Glemham</hi> gaines renowne,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of thoſe which at his weale doth frowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sweete man of worth, <hi>Mars</hi> new adopted ſonne,</l>
               <l>Let windes and ſeas, ſubiect themſelues for thee,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Albion</hi> Ile, thou ſafety maiſt returne,</l>
               <l>Fraughted with Gold, and Pearle of <hi>Indee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ioy of freends, thy preſence wiſh to ſee,</l>
               <l>Whoſe honors gaind, with danger on the flood,</l>
               <l>Doth glad their harts, that wiſh our countries good.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
